<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>thoughts</title>
  <subtitle>because deliberation informs action</subtitle>
  <id>http://jceipek.com/articles</id>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/articles"/>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-10-25T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Beyond Defaults: A Philosophy of Learning through Representation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/26/learning-philosophy.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/26/learning-philosophy.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-25T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-26T17:45:51-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a personal philosophy that is all about learning: I can't be happy unless I'm doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notion is aligned with Raph Coster's arguments in &lt;em&gt;A Theory of Fun for Game Design&lt;/em&gt;; he cites &lt;em&gt;Tic-Tac-Toe&lt;/em&gt; as an example of a game that is only fun for children until they learn to recognize the patterns in the game. Under trivial optimal play, every match will end in a stalemate, and the game becomes boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As media designers, we frequently struggle to create "engaging" content. One simple way to do this is to ensure that everything we create teaches something. Think of all the books we enjoy even more deeply when we reread them. We say things like "there are so many amazing things I missed when I read it the first time."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of "deep", "strategic" play in great games: it's well-accepted that each time we play them, we find new strategies and new meaning in the game mechanics. However, games aren't just about mechanics, they are also about representation through visuals, audio, and other means. It should be obvious that representation and mechanics together influence what we (consciously or not) learn from games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a shooting game, it matters whether the entities we shoot are vicious demons (&lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt;, 1993) or unarmed civilians (&lt;em&gt;Hatred&lt;/em&gt;, planned 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing a game, there is a big tendency to rely on defaults, on representations that match unconscious cultural or social stereotypes. The problem with that approach is that the resulting games have a tendency to have white cisgender male characters, to disempower and objectify female characters, and to portray black characters as agents of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Power of Play: The Portrayal and Performance of Race in Video Games&lt;/em&gt;, Everett and Watkins examine some of negative stereotypes reinforced by racial representation in games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can use representations to teach and games are fun and engaging when we can learn from them, won't games be all the more engaging if the representations in them introduce us to new contexts?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Programming vs Games in Discourse</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/12/programming-vs-games.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/12/programming-vs-games.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-11T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-13T01:19:42-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The general discussion on the merits of games seems very similar to the general discussion regarding those of programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="programming-and-games-as-a-distraction-from-what-is-important"&gt;Programming and Games as a Distraction from "What is Important"&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"When will you stop playing games and get back to work?"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often view games as a distraction, as a 'fun' respite from the cold realities of life and work. This is the mindset that led one of my colleagues to say "I just don't have time for games."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, our technology-saturated culture is so focused on programming as a work-related pursuit that we can find it difficult to draw a parallel with programming, but I think "Stop sitting in front of a computer screen and go outside!" is still a common sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gamesprogramming-as-treatment"&gt;Games/Programming as Treatment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/MeanwhileAtCodeOrg/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;meanwhile, at code.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bret Victor bemoans the corruption of Seymour Papert's thoughts on programming and pedagogy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Papert's goal was to give children a path to powerful mathematical
ideas, and he saw programming as a better carrier of the ideas than
pencil-and-paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Others misinterpret him as making the dubious claim that
&lt;strong&gt;simply learning to program will make you think better&lt;/strong&gt;.
Papert is astonished that anyone would think he was saying that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the work on &lt;em&gt;gamification of education&lt;/em&gt; takes a similar approach, treating games as a "more fun" or less teacher-intensive method to transmit knowledge through rote memorization and award structures supported by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operant_conditioning_chamber"&gt;Skinner box&lt;/a&gt; mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gamesprogramming-and-encoded-ideas"&gt;Games/Programming and Encoded Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bret Victor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Papert explains that programming can serve as a medium in which
powerful ideas can be brought within reach. But the focus, of course,
must be on the powerful ideas, not the programming itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.arts.rpi.edu/~ruiz/EGDFall10/readings/RhetoricVideoGames_Bogost.pdf"&gt;The Rhetoric of Video Games&lt;/a&gt;, Ian Bogost argues that games represent a powerful way of representing ideas that other media cannot as readily communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the connection between games and programming in discourse isn't truly surprising, because both involve encoding and exploring procedural behavior. In the strictest sense, all games are programs, but that fact is easy to forget because we usually think of programs as computer software while games more readily call to mind social or physical interactions. Nonetheless, I think recognizing something in one domain can help us reconsider our views on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Unstructured Plots?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/04/unstructured-plots.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/04/unstructured-plots.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-03T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-04T23:15:04-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At a panel at GDC, Tom Abernathy (Riot Games narrative lead) and Richard Rouse III (designer at Microsoft Game Studios) asserted that plot is "highly overrated" in games, that players are less likely to remember the plots for their favorite games than their favorite movies, and that games should stop pursuing a three act narrative structure in favor of unstructured stories that focus on characters. See &lt;a href="http://www.polygon.com/2014/3/17/5519684/narrative-designers-benefits-of-ditching-the-three-act"&gt;Narrative designers discuss benefits of ditching the three act structure&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my own experiences, the longer and more complex a storyline is, the less likely I am to remember it, especially if it is interrupted by sequences that provide no discernible story progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"Game narrative is almost always extremely spaced out," Abernathy said.
"There might be ongoing narratives with individual characters, but plot
twists that come every 90 minutes or so happen right before you are about to
get back into the gameplay and you're less likely to remember it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all our favorite story games provide 'story' in the form of cutscenes that interrupt gameplay every 90 minutes or so, then yes, it is quite clear that we will have trouble remembering the 'plot' in those games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I can think of many examples in other media that suffer from the same problem: interrupting main plot progression with convoluted side stories, long-winded descriptions (certain fantasy books are particularly at fault here), long and flashy action sequences (most modern action movies), etc…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the reason players can remember the stories in their favorite movies more readily than in their favorite games is that the games simply employ comparatively poor storytelling techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best told stories, regardless of medium, rely on disordering incidents, on frequent character development, on understandable motivations, and on interaction between characters. The stories in games like &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ghost Trick&lt;/em&gt; are particularly well executed in this regard, and I can remember their plots quite well as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improv-heavy role playing game &lt;a href="http://www.bullypulpitgames.com/games/fiasco/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fiasco&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; makes character interaction part of its core mechanic; it consists of scenes in which players assume the roles of characters attempting to achieve specific goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases where we want to tell stories with our media, I think what we really want is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; structure, rather than less.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Game Webserial</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/28/the-game-webserial.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/28/the-game-webserial.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-27T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-28T13:17:48-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some of the most enduring online communities gather around &lt;em&gt;webserials&lt;/em&gt; (serialized online fiction like &lt;a href="http://parahumans.wordpress.com/about/"&gt;Worm&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;em&gt;webcomics&lt;/em&gt; (generally serialized online comics like &lt;a href="http://questionablecontent.net/"&gt;Questionable Content&lt;/a&gt;), and &lt;em&gt;web series&lt;/em&gt; (serialized online video series like &lt;a href="http://watchtheguild.com"&gt;The Guild&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we traverse the spectrum from static text to the moving image, we see the complexity of authoring these types of experiences increase dramatically, although there isn't as much variation in production times as one might expect. While some webserials update several times a week and some webcomics take &lt;a href="http://dresdencodak.com/2010/06/03/dark-science-01/"&gt;several months to create&lt;/a&gt;, we can also find well-produced video content updated on a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/show/freddiew"&gt;weekly basis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interactive medium is conspiciously absent from this list. While some &lt;a href="https://www.telltalegames.com"&gt;fantastic episodic games exist&lt;/a&gt;, they are generally released as downloadable titles with months or years between releases. The idea of a single creator or small group regularly releasing games is &lt;a href="http://www.lessmilk.com/12games"&gt;not unheard of&lt;/a&gt;, I know of no serialized online games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will "Game Webserials" ever become popular? What form will the episodic 30 second - 30 minute online game take? Will it be a classic point-and-click adventure with a linear storyline? Will it be a procedural world with new content produced each week? Perhaps something we've never seen before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are the tools we have to create these experiences approachable and advanced enough to make this kind of creation feasible for creators as diverse as those who create more traditional webserials?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A "Magic Threshold"</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/21/magic-threshold.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/21/magic-threshold.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-20T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-21T13:22:42-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;There is No Magic Circle&lt;/em&gt; (2009), Consalvo argues that games cannot be viewed from a purely structural perspective, that Huizinga's "magic circle" is absurd given its implication that the ordinary rules of everyday life no longer apply within its confines. Instead, we must recognize that the ordinary rules very well do apply "in addition to, in competition with, other rules and in relation to multiple contexts, across varying cultures, and into different groups, legal situations, and homes."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, I think the concept of a magic circle as a boundary between the mindset for being in a game and outside a game is still very valuable. &lt;em&gt;Context is everything&lt;/em&gt; when it comes to games and play. For example, when we speak of "cat and mouse" games, we mean that the cat is turning what would otherwise be a hunt into a form of play. From the mouse' perspective, there is no game, simply a struggle for everyday survival. In the 1997 film &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0119174/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Game&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the protagonist participates in an experience that he percieves as a game others are playing with him rather than a game that he is playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As UX designers, I think we need to ensure that the experiences we create respect this distinction by making passage through the &lt;em&gt;magic threshold&lt;/em&gt; and back very clear to our users and players.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Narrative</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/14/on-narrative.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/14/on-narrative.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-13T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-14T12:48:05-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2002, Henry Jenkins published the article &lt;em&gt;Game Design as Narrative Architecture&lt;/em&gt;. In it, he addresses many of my misgivings about the views Jesper Juul expresses in his &lt;em&gt;A Clash Between Games and Narrative&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Games Telling Stories?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following decade, we have witnessed the emergence of many innovative experiences that have advanced the state of the art in many of the categories Jenkins proposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transmedia-storytelling"&gt;Transmedia Storytelling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experience franchises spreading to diverse media is nothing new. Look no further than the superhero characters from comics appearing in books, movies, television, web-series, and games. More interesting is the phenomenon of interactive experiences that transcend media boundaries. A recent example is Google's Ingress, a worldwide multiplayer alternate reality game that enables player participation through smartphone-world interaction, online code breaking, and storytelling/partaking through online videos and social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spatial-narratives"&gt;Spatial Narratives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gone Home&lt;/em&gt; is a perfect example of what Jenkins calls a "Memory Palace," a place that players can explore at will, unravelling stories left in narrative fragments throughout a space. While &lt;em&gt;Gone Home&lt;/em&gt; communicates one primary narrative, that of the protagonist's sister, it also contains several tangentially-related story threads involving the other members of the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="micronarratives"&gt;Micronarratives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most modern games, particularly big budget titles, embed many "memorable moments" into their games. Some of these are developed to the extent that they are known as "side-quests," with mostly self-contained, sometimes optional narrative arcs that may enhance the primary storyline or serve as exercises in world-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Punch Drunk's &lt;em&gt;Sleep No More&lt;/em&gt; is particularly notable in this category. It encourages audiences to explore a mass of related but distinct narrative threads at their own pace as they follow actors and explore a physical three story building with maze-like passages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="emergent-narratives"&gt;Emergent Narratives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unplanned narratives often emerge from games with large player-bases. The space game &lt;em&gt;Eve Online&lt;/em&gt; is a prime example; it provides a sandbox-like simulation environment with enough constraints that players self-organize to take on roles in many different stories involving themes such as faction conflict, diplomacy, corporate espionage, and piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me, however, that very few experiences explore smaller-scale emergent storytelling, especially in the category of single-player computer games with an emphasis on player choice. Some of the best games in this category (such as the fantastic &lt;em&gt;Spelunky&lt;/em&gt;) involve procedurally generated worlds and enemies and explore few emotions unrelated to conquest.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
