<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>thoughts</title>
  <subtitle>because deliberation informs action</subtitle>
  <id>http://jceipek.com/articles</id>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/articles"/>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-11-28T16:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Managing Complexity: Spelunky vs League of Legends</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/29/managing-complexity.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/29/managing-complexity.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-28T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-30T23:05:01-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not afraid of complexity. As I've mentioned in the past, I love learning new things across many different domains, from mathematics to art to experience design. However, some things are easier to learn than others because of their mental models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to learn things that behave in accordance with your expectations, and learning something new that builds on your existing understanding of the world is relatively simple. Learning something that doesn't is much harder. Someone who speaks two romance languages probably won't have as much trouble learning a new romance language as learning Chinese, for example. Someone who experiences math as formula memorization probably won't be able to apply Calculus outside of the classroom context within which they learned it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I went to a Thanksgiving party, helped make and eat lots of great food, and played digital games with some of my friends. Among them were Spelunky and a 5v5 game of League of Legends (a MOBA commonly known as LOL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spelunky and LOL are fantastically complex. They each have many items and characters, each with different properties that substantially affect gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While becoming proficient at these games is quite challenging, the different ways in which they manage complexity makes Spelunky much easier to understand than LOL, and I think it has a much better overall design as a result. Why does Spelunky excel where LOL falls short?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consistency&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;To be consistent, a system has to follow its own rules and conventions. Spelunky is very consistent. Treasure chests always contain items. Gold bars give you a predictable amount of gold. You can only carry one thing in your hands. The environment is deadly. Even though every level is procedurally generated, it will always have one exit that leads to the next level. Every game has the same progression of stages.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;LOL has problems with consistency, especially with respect to items and the item shop:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Item Shop" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-29-managing-complexity/ItemShop.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;LOL has many different items that all fall into different categories. The most important ones (from what I can tell as a first-time player) are consumable (single-use), passive (always in-use), or active (need to be triggered with an associated cooldown).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;However, the item shop doesn't use that classification for items. All the items look consistent even though they aren't. Players can switch to the list of all items to see this:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="All Item Shop Items" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-29-managing-complexity/ItemShopAll.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Since LOL is a fast-paced game of team competition, the only way to make effective item choices is to memorize the descriptions of the items to determine how they work when the game isn't running.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Even more problematic is the "trinket" slot next to the 6 other item slots. A certain type of item, called a trinket/ward can only fill that one spot. Again, the store presents this item type consistently with the others. When I had filled 6 of my item slots, I couldn't understand why I couldn't buy another item even though I still had an empty slot. Since 6 of my slots were filled, the only visual distinction (the low-contrast eye emblem) failed to help me differentiate the function of the 7th slot from the others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Affordances&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;An affordance is part of a system that broadcasts its use by its form. Door plates afford pushing while vertical door handles afford pulling. The spikes in Spelunky look particularly deadly – and they are. The only locked chest in Spelunky has a large golden lock with a matching golden key, and the purpose of the key is evident from its appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;LOL has many poor affordances. Why does clicking on the store (which looks similar to the other buildings) make a modal dialog fill the screen, but clicking on the other buildings does not? Why do radar dishes on the ground explode when you get close to them when real radar dishes are used to scan objects at a distance?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Feedback&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;True learning comes at the price of repeated failure. When something doesn't behave as you expect, you adjust your expectations based on your experiences. When a system encourages failing fast and provides good feedback that helps you understand your mistakes, you can build a better mental model of the system more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Spelunky is a brutal game; death means restarting from the beginning. However, it associates every failure with the feedback you need in order to prevent making the same mistake again. Since every playthrough is different but pits you against a new configuration of the same obstacles, the game encourages true learning rather than memorizing a sequence of actions.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Theoretically, LOL has a framework for providing much more relevant feedback than Spelunky because death means respawning back at the base. In fact, LOL does use feedback to manage complexity more effectively than consistency and affordances. LOL displays a death recap modal after every death. While this modal is probably extrordinarily useful to intermediate players, it didn't help me, as a beginner, understand many of my deaths because they were so sudden and revolved around placement as much as on the abilities of the other players. I think LOL beginners would benefit from a death replay similar to Towerfall Ascension, a game that also has very rapid deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Death Recap" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-29-managing-complexity/DeathRecap.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spelunky is an original title while League of Legends was inspired by a mod of Warcraft III called Defense of the Ancients. LOL is built around mental models that don't make much sense in the context of a standalone game. Consequently, it would probably be much harder to perfect LOL than to create a much better game by making a completely original MOBA (a path a number of other games have attempted). Nonetheless, I think LOL could be substantially improved with more thought given to consistency, affordances, and feedback while still meeting the needs of its legacy userbase.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Problem with Video Tutorials</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/23/video-tutorials.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/23/video-tutorials.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-22T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-24T03:10:17-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I try to spend most of my time learning new things. Some of the things I've been learning most recently include how to bake, how to make props, how to program in Clojurescript, and how to work with Quaternions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I need to use a lot of software to create interactive media, learning to use software and programming APIs is part of my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, the major software teaching approaches on the internet fall into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Q&amp;amp;A Style Forums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Text Tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Video Tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like forum style answers from sites like Stack Overflow because they answer specific questions and are easily searchable. However, because they are so limited in scope, they are rarely effective at providing introductions to techniques; deferring to text or video tutorials for that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like text tutorials because they are easily glanceable. If the tutorial is well-organized, I can easily find the answer to my specific question without having to waste my time by wading through explanations of things I already know. Unfortunately, text is static and can't convey complex visual techniques. Well-chosen and annotated images can help to alleviate this problem, but they can't replace someone actually demonstrating how to do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demonstration is the selling point of video tutorials. Recording a video of doing something seems much easier than writing a comprehensive explanation. Because of this apparently low barrier to entry, the quantity of video tutorials far outstrips the quantity of other software explanations on the internet. Ultimately, video tutorials have two severe flaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are not glanceable. Skimming a video of a software demonstration isn't very helpful because the audio is just as or more important than the visuals. Most video player interfaces are designed around watching a video from start to finish. Tutorials do not benefit from this structure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are easy to structure poorly. While making a well-structured video tutorial is actually much harder than creating a well-structured text tutorial; it just seems easier to get started with a video tutorial: you're just talking to a camera, how hard could that be?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best tutorials and explanations consist of a hybrid of text, video, and interactivity. Using this approach, teachers can create well-structured, glanceable representations that allow learners to experiment in the context of the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bret Victor has created some early experiments in this direction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/#!/LearnableProgramming"&gt;http://worrydream.com/#!/LearnableProgramming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/#!/MediaForThinkingTheUnthinkable"&gt;http://worrydream.com/#!/MediaForThinkingTheUnthinkable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/#!/ScientificCommunicationAsSequentialArt"&gt;http://worrydream.com/#!/ScientificCommunicationAsSequentialArt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Direct Manipulation Tool Construction</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/19/direct-manipulation-tool-construction.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/19/direct-manipulation-tool-construction.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-18T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-20T02:45:43-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been busy exchanging skills with my classmates at &lt;a href="http://interactive.usc.edu"&gt;USC's graduate Interactive Media and Games Division&lt;/a&gt;. I taught Unity programming and learned prop making and baking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Skitter Mask" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-19-direct-manipulation-tool-construction/mask.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Journey Cake" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-19-direct-manipulation-tool-construction/cake.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these arts revolve around direct manipulation; you bend foam and fondant, cut components into the right shape, and use tools to shape your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that the end result rarely matches the original designs, and that this is a Very Good Thing. Working on physical objects involves many implicit constraints that shape the end result and inspire solutions that would otherwise never have been considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the power of direct manipulation: constantly getting feedback as you are working and changing your work in response to that feedback. Interfaces (and more generally, systems) without constant feedback are inherently limited to an initial design, which is a problem because, as you work, you often realize that the original design is flawed. For a commonly accepted example of this in software and engineering, consider the derided &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model"&gt;Waterfall&lt;/a&gt; development technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with physical materials, I constantly felt the urge to improvise. If I didn't have a tool I thought I would need, I would take a minute or two to create an ad-hoc tool for the specific task I was working on at the time. How can I bend this part into the shape that I want? I can just use a bowl. I'm missing a rolling pin small enough to flatten this gum paste, so I'll use this thin wooden dowel. How can I draw a large perfect circle without a compass? I'll tape two pencils to a wooden board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the ease with which you can construct useful one-off tools through direct manipulation is sorely lacking in the digital space. Yes, some interfaces are scriptable through simple programming languages like Lua and Python, but the barrier to entry is much higher than taping miscellany together. Moreover, since it is so hard to make a tool to begin with, once you have decided to make it, you are much more inclined to waste the time you could have been using to make the thing you were working on by making the tool 'reusable' even if you'll only actually need it once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest analogue I can think of to direct manipulation tool construction in the software space is a recorded macro that can automate repetitive actions. Unfortunately, they are a poor substitute for the flexibility of making your own tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our software involves so little user feedback and so much indirect manipulation of hidden state (see Bret Victor's &lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/LearnableProgramming/"&gt;Learnable Programming)&lt;/a&gt;), I don't think we can do much better than macros and scripting languages. If you can directly manipulate something, you can have many more opportunities to easily make your own tools. Play &lt;a href="http://euclidthegame.com"&gt;Euclid: The Game&lt;/a&gt; to get an inkling of what that might be like.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Show me the Data: Learning Math through Exploration</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/09/learning-math-through-exploration.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/09/learning-math-through-exploration.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-08T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-10T00:47:14-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scalars. Vectors. Matrices. Quaternions. Most digital games are full of geometric mathematical manipulations and concepts. All games that represent movement visually through screens or projectors involve some form of conceptual mapping from abstract mathematical spaces to concrete geometric spaces we can see. Pac-man projects a toroidal space onto a 2d cartesian plane. Most 3d games involve transformations in a 3d cartesian space that are ultimately projected on a flat screen. Some, like the upcoming 4d puzzle game &lt;a href="http://miegakure.com"&gt;Miegakure&lt;/a&gt;, involve even more complex spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most of us have at least some experience playing these games on our phones, computers, and consoles from a young age, we tend not to think about the mathematical manipulations directly. Instead, we think about how our actions as players affect the 2d image that we can see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional math classes teach geometry through proofs and formulas, involving students in memorization and symbolic manipulation. Some of the students can see beyond the drudgery in these tasks to the elegance of the actual mathematics. Those are the students who will become mathematicians, engineers, and computer graphics experts. The rest become bored and go on to avoid "math" in their lives as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think seeing and changing the hidden transformations in some games, perhaps through visual debug modes, could help us form more accurate mental models of geometry while contextualizing its importance in the media with which we interact on a frequent basis.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Games that Invite Change</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/02/games-that-invite-change.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/02/games-that-invite-change.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-01T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-02T20:28:47-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The element that substantially differentiates games from other media is the degree to which they enable and encourage audience participation. Games respond when the audience acts. We might say that paintings, film, and novels, also respond, in that each audience member brings a context and set of interpretations to these media forms. However, games are much more dynamic. The best games encourage players to experiment with the mechanics in as many different ways as possible. Jonathan Blow's game design philosophy revolves around guiding players to discover the deep emergent consequences of a simple and elegant ruleset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all games encourage interaction, some actually invite players to explore the consequences of modifying their systems, to add or remove rules and mechanics and to explore the implications of those changes. These games are inherently moddable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some games are so compactly designed that changing them effectively would be very difficult. As I discussed &lt;a href="http://jceipek.com/thoughts/#2014/09/01-Set-System-Analysis"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, the card game &lt;em&gt;Set&lt;/em&gt; discourages modding because any alterations would oppose the simplicity and elegance of the core system design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've been working on a creative problem solving card game called &lt;em&gt;Evil Lairs for Dummies&lt;/em&gt;. We designed it to be moddable, to have systems that beg the players to change them to see what will happen. However, we didn't frame the game in a way that invited this type of change; the players felt that they didn't have permission to mod the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for a game to truly invite change, I think it needs to be explicitly encouraged by the designers and the game systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beyond Defaults: A Philosophy of Learning through Representation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/26/learning-philosophy.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/26/learning-philosophy.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-25T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-26T17:45:51-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a personal philosophy that is all about learning: I can't be happy unless I'm doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notion is aligned with Raph Coster's arguments in &lt;em&gt;A Theory of Fun for Game Design&lt;/em&gt;; he cites &lt;em&gt;Tic-Tac-Toe&lt;/em&gt; as an example of a game that is only fun for children until they learn to recognize the patterns in the game. Under trivial optimal play, every match will end in a stalemate, and the game becomes boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As media designers, we frequently struggle to create "engaging" content. One simple way to do this is to ensure that everything we create teaches something. Think of all the books we enjoy even more deeply when we reread them. We say things like "there are so many amazing things I missed when I read it the first time."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of "deep", "strategic" play in great games: it's well-accepted that each time we play them, we find new strategies and new meaning in the game mechanics. However, games aren't just about mechanics, they are also about representation through visuals, audio, and other means. It should be obvious that representation and mechanics together influence what we (consciously or not) learn from games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a shooting game, it matters whether the entities we shoot are vicious demons (&lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt;, 1993) or unarmed civilians (&lt;em&gt;Hatred&lt;/em&gt;, planned 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing a game, there is a big tendency to rely on defaults, on representations that match unconscious cultural or social stereotypes. The problem with that approach is that the resulting games have a tendency to have white cisgender male characters, to disempower and objectify female characters, and to portray black characters as agents of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Power of Play: The Portrayal and Performance of Race in Video Games&lt;/em&gt;, Everett and Watkins examine some of negative stereotypes reinforced by racial representation in games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can use representations to teach and games are fun and engaging when we can learn from them, won't games be all the more engaging if the representations in them introduce us to new contexts?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
