<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>thoughts</title>
  <subtitle>because deliberation informs action</subtitle>
  <id>http://jceipek.com/articles</id>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/articles"/>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-11-18T16:00:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Direct Manipulation Tool Construction</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/19/direct-manipulation-tool-construction.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/19/direct-manipulation-tool-construction.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-18T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-20T02:45:43-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been busy exchanging skills with my classmates at &lt;a href="http://interactive.usc.edu"&gt;USC's graduate Interactive Media and Games Division&lt;/a&gt;. I taught Unity programming and learned prop making and baking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Skitter Mask" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-19-direct-manipulation-tool-construction/mask.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Journey Cake" src="/thoughts/images/2014-11-19-direct-manipulation-tool-construction/cake.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these arts revolve around direct manipulation; you bend foam and fondant, cut components into the right shape, and use tools to shape your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that the end result rarely matches the original designs, and that this is a Very Good Thing. Working on physical objects involves many implicit constraints that shape the end result and inspire solutions that would otherwise never have been considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the power of direct manipulation: constantly getting feedback as you are working and changing your work in response to that feedback. Interfaces (and more generally, systems) without constant feedback are inherently limited to an initial design, which is a problem because, as you work, you often realize that the original design is flawed. For a commonly accepted example of this in software and engineering, consider the derided &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model"&gt;Waterfall&lt;/a&gt; development technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with physical materials, I constantly felt the urge to improvise. If I didn't have a tool I thought I would need, I would take a minute or two to create an ad-hoc tool for the specific task I was working on at the time. How can I bend this part into the shape that I want? I can just use a bowl. I'm missing a rolling pin small enough to flatten this gum paste, so I'll use this thin wooden dowel. How can I draw a large perfect circle without a compass? I'll tape two pencils to a wooden board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the ease with which you can construct useful one-off tools through direct manipulation is sorely lacking in the digital space. Yes, some interfaces are scriptable through simple programming languages like Lua and Python, but the barrier to entry is much higher than taping miscellany together. Moreover, since it is so hard to make a tool to begin with, once you have decided to make it, you are much more inclined to waste the time you could have been using to make the thing you were working on by making the tool 'reusable' even if you'll only actually need it once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest analogue I can think of to direct manipulation tool construction in the software space is a recorded macro that can automate repetitive actions. Unfortunately, they are a poor substitute for the flexibility of making your own tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our software involves so little user feedback and so much indirect manipulation of hidden state (see Bret Victor's &lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/LearnableProgramming/"&gt;Learnable Programming)&lt;/a&gt;), I don't think we can do much better than macros and scripting languages. If you can directly manipulate something, you can have many more opportunities to easily make your own tools. Play &lt;a href="http://euclidthegame.com"&gt;Euclid: The Game&lt;/a&gt; to get an inkling of what that might be like.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Show me the Data: Learning Math through Exploration</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/09/learning-math-through-exploration.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/09/learning-math-through-exploration.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-08T16:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-10T00:47:14-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scalars. Vectors. Matrices. Quaternions. Most digital games are full of geometric mathematical manipulations and concepts. All games that represent movement visually through screens or projectors involve some form of conceptual mapping from abstract mathematical spaces to concrete geometric spaces we can see. Pac-man projects a toroidal space onto a 2d cartesian plane. Most 3d games involve transformations in a 3d cartesian space that are ultimately projected on a flat screen. Some, like the upcoming 4d puzzle game &lt;a href="http://miegakure.com"&gt;Miegakure&lt;/a&gt;, involve even more complex spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although most of us have at least some experience playing these games on our phones, computers, and consoles from a young age, we tend not to think about the mathematical manipulations directly. Instead, we think about how our actions as players affect the 2d image that we can see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional math classes teach geometry through proofs and formulas, involving students in memorization and symbolic manipulation. Some of the students can see beyond the drudgery in these tasks to the elegance of the actual mathematics. Those are the students who will become mathematicians, engineers, and computer graphics experts. The rest become bored and go on to avoid "math" in their lives as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think seeing and changing the hidden transformations in some games, perhaps through visual debug modes, could help us form more accurate mental models of geometry while contextualizing its importance in the media with which we interact on a frequent basis.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Games that Invite Change</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/02/games-that-invite-change.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/11/02/games-that-invite-change.html</id>
    <published>2014-11-01T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-11-02T20:28:47-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The element that substantially differentiates games from other media is the degree to which they enable and encourage audience participation. Games respond when the audience acts. We might say that paintings, film, and novels, also respond, in that each audience member brings a context and set of interpretations to these media forms. However, games are much more dynamic. The best games encourage players to experiment with the mechanics in as many different ways as possible. Jonathan Blow's game design philosophy revolves around guiding players to discover the deep emergent consequences of a simple and elegant ruleset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all games encourage interaction, some actually invite players to explore the consequences of modifying their systems, to add or remove rules and mechanics and to explore the implications of those changes. These games are inherently moddable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some games are so compactly designed that changing them effectively would be very difficult. As I discussed &lt;a href="http://jceipek.com/thoughts/#2014/09/01-Set-System-Analysis"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, the card game &lt;em&gt;Set&lt;/em&gt; discourages modding because any alterations would oppose the simplicity and elegance of the core system design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've been working on a creative problem solving card game called &lt;em&gt;Evil Lairs for Dummies&lt;/em&gt;. We designed it to be moddable, to have systems that beg the players to change them to see what will happen. However, we didn't frame the game in a way that invited this type of change; the players felt that they didn't have permission to mod the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for a game to truly invite change, I think it needs to be explicitly encouraged by the designers and the game systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beyond Defaults: A Philosophy of Learning through Representation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/26/learning-philosophy.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/26/learning-philosophy.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-25T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-26T17:45:51-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a personal philosophy that is all about learning: I can't be happy unless I'm doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notion is aligned with Raph Coster's arguments in &lt;em&gt;A Theory of Fun for Game Design&lt;/em&gt;; he cites &lt;em&gt;Tic-Tac-Toe&lt;/em&gt; as an example of a game that is only fun for children until they learn to recognize the patterns in the game. Under trivial optimal play, every match will end in a stalemate, and the game becomes boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As media designers, we frequently struggle to create "engaging" content. One simple way to do this is to ensure that everything we create teaches something. Think of all the books we enjoy even more deeply when we reread them. We say things like "there are so many amazing things I missed when I read it the first time."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of "deep", "strategic" play in great games: it's well-accepted that each time we play them, we find new strategies and new meaning in the game mechanics. However, games aren't just about mechanics, they are also about representation through visuals, audio, and other means. It should be obvious that representation and mechanics together influence what we (consciously or not) learn from games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a shooting game, it matters whether the entities we shoot are vicious demons (&lt;em&gt;Doom&lt;/em&gt;, 1993) or unarmed civilians (&lt;em&gt;Hatred&lt;/em&gt;, planned 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing a game, there is a big tendency to rely on defaults, on representations that match unconscious cultural or social stereotypes. The problem with that approach is that the resulting games have a tendency to have white cisgender male characters, to disempower and objectify female characters, and to portray black characters as agents of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Power of Play: The Portrayal and Performance of Race in Video Games&lt;/em&gt;, Everett and Watkins examine some of negative stereotypes reinforced by racial representation in games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can use representations to teach and games are fun and engaging when we can learn from them, won't games be all the more engaging if the representations in them introduce us to new contexts?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Programming vs Games in Discourse</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/12/programming-vs-games.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/12/programming-vs-games.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-11T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-13T01:19:42-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The general discussion on the merits of games seems very similar to the general discussion regarding those of programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="programming-and-games-as-a-distraction-from-what-is-important"&gt;Programming and Games as a Distraction from "What is Important"&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"When will you stop playing games and get back to work?"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often view games as a distraction, as a 'fun' respite from the cold realities of life and work. This is the mindset that led one of my colleagues to say "I just don't have time for games."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, our technology-saturated culture is so focused on programming as a work-related pursuit that we can find it difficult to draw a parallel with programming, but I think "Stop sitting in front of a computer screen and go outside!" is still a common sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gamesprogramming-as-treatment"&gt;Games/Programming as Treatment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://worrydream.com/MeanwhileAtCodeOrg/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;meanwhile, at code.org&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Bret Victor bemoans the corruption of Seymour Papert's thoughts on programming and pedagogy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Papert's goal was to give children a path to powerful mathematical
ideas, and he saw programming as a better carrier of the ideas than
pencil-and-paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Others misinterpret him as making the dubious claim that
&lt;strong&gt;simply learning to program will make you think better&lt;/strong&gt;.
Papert is astonished that anyone would think he was saying that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the work on &lt;em&gt;gamification of education&lt;/em&gt; takes a similar approach, treating games as a "more fun" or less teacher-intensive method to transmit knowledge through rote memorization and award structures supported by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operant_conditioning_chamber"&gt;Skinner box&lt;/a&gt; mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="gamesprogramming-and-encoded-ideas"&gt;Games/Programming and Encoded Ideas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bret Victor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Papert explains that programming can serve as a medium in which
powerful ideas can be brought within reach. But the focus, of course,
must be on the powerful ideas, not the programming itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.arts.rpi.edu/~ruiz/EGDFall10/readings/RhetoricVideoGames_Bogost.pdf"&gt;The Rhetoric of Video Games&lt;/a&gt;, Ian Bogost argues that games represent a powerful way of representing ideas that other media cannot as readily communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the connection between games and programming in discourse isn't truly surprising, because both involve encoding and exploring procedural behavior. In the strictest sense, all games are programs, but that fact is easy to forget because we usually think of programs as computer software while games more readily call to mind social or physical interactions. Nonetheless, I think recognizing something in one domain can help us reconsider our views on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Unstructured Plots?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/04/unstructured-plots.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/10/04/unstructured-plots.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-03T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-04T23:15:04-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At a panel at GDC, Tom Abernathy (Riot Games narrative lead) and Richard Rouse III (designer at Microsoft Game Studios) asserted that plot is "highly overrated" in games, that players are less likely to remember the plots for their favorite games than their favorite movies, and that games should stop pursuing a three act narrative structure in favor of unstructured stories that focus on characters. See &lt;a href="http://www.polygon.com/2014/3/17/5519684/narrative-designers-benefits-of-ditching-the-three-act"&gt;Narrative designers discuss benefits of ditching the three act structure&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my own experiences, the longer and more complex a storyline is, the less likely I am to remember it, especially if it is interrupted by sequences that provide no discernible story progression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"Game narrative is almost always extremely spaced out," Abernathy said.
"There might be ongoing narratives with individual characters, but plot
twists that come every 90 minutes or so happen right before you are about to
get back into the gameplay and you're less likely to remember it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all our favorite story games provide 'story' in the form of cutscenes that interrupt gameplay every 90 minutes or so, then yes, it is quite clear that we will have trouble remembering the 'plot' in those games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I can think of many examples in other media that suffer from the same problem: interrupting main plot progression with convoluted side stories, long-winded descriptions (certain fantasy books are particularly at fault here), long and flashy action sequences (most modern action movies), etc…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the reason players can remember the stories in their favorite movies more readily than in their favorite games is that the games simply employ comparatively poor storytelling techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best told stories, regardless of medium, rely on disordering incidents, on frequent character development, on understandable motivations, and on interaction between characters. The stories in games like &lt;em&gt;Portal&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ghost Trick&lt;/em&gt; are particularly well executed in this regard, and I can remember their plots quite well as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improv-heavy role playing game &lt;a href="http://www.bullypulpitgames.com/games/fiasco/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fiasco&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; makes character interaction part of its core mechanic; it consists of scenes in which players assume the roles of characters attempting to achieve specific goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases where we want to tell stories with our media, I think what we really want is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; structure, rather than less.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
