<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>thoughts</title>
  <subtitle>because deliberation informs action</subtitle>
  <id>http://jceipek.com/articles</id>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/articles"/>
  <link href="http://jceipek.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-09-27T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The Game Webserial</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/28/the-game-webserial.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/28/the-game-webserial.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-27T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-28T13:17:48-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some of the most enduring online communities gather around &lt;em&gt;webserials&lt;/em&gt; (serialized online fiction like &lt;a href="http://parahumans.wordpress.com/about/"&gt;Worm&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;em&gt;webcomics&lt;/em&gt; (generally serialized online comics like &lt;a href="http://questionablecontent.net/"&gt;Questionable Content&lt;/a&gt;), and &lt;em&gt;web series&lt;/em&gt; (serialized online video series like &lt;a href="http://watchtheguild.com"&gt;The Guild&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we traverse the spectrum from static text to the moving image, we see the complexity of authoring these types of experiences increase dramatically, although there isn't as much variation in production times as one might expect. While some webserials update several times a week and some webcomics take &lt;a href="http://dresdencodak.com/2010/06/03/dark-science-01/"&gt;several months to create&lt;/a&gt;, we can also find well-produced video content updated on a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/show/freddiew"&gt;weekly basis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interactive medium is conspiciously absent from this list. While some &lt;a href="https://www.telltalegames.com"&gt;fantastic episodic games exist&lt;/a&gt;, they are generally released as downloadable titles with months or years between releases. The idea of a single creator or small group regularly releasing games is &lt;a href="http://www.lessmilk.com/12games"&gt;not unheard of&lt;/a&gt;, I know of no serialized online games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will "Game Webserials" ever become popular? What form will the episodic 30 second - 30 minute online game take? Will it be a classic point-and-click adventure with a linear storyline? Will it be a procedural world with new content produced each week? Perhaps something we've never seen before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are the tools we have to create these experiences approachable and advanced enough to make this kind of creation feasible for creators as diverse as those who create more traditional webserials?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A "Magic Threshold"</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/21/magic-threshold.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/21/magic-threshold.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-20T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-21T13:22:42-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;There is No Magic Circle&lt;/em&gt; (2009), Consalvo argues that games cannot be viewed from a purely structural perspective, that Huizinga's "magic circle" is absurd given its implication that the ordinary rules of everyday life no longer apply within its confines. Instead, we must recognize that the ordinary rules very well do apply "in addition to, in competition with, other rules and in relation to multiple contexts, across varying cultures, and into different groups, legal situations, and homes."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, I think the concept of a magic circle as a boundary between the mindset for being in a game and outside a game is still very valuable. &lt;em&gt;Context is everything&lt;/em&gt; when it comes to games and play. For example, when we speak of "cat and mouse" games, we mean that the cat is turning what would otherwise be a hunt into a form of play. From the mouse' perspective, there is no game, simply a struggle for everyday survival. In the 1997 film &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0119174/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Game&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the protagonist participates in an experience that he percieves as a game others are playing with him rather than a game that he is playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As UX designers, I think we need to ensure that the experiences we create respect this distinction by making passage through the &lt;em&gt;magic threshold&lt;/em&gt; and back very clear to our users and players.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Narrative</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/14/on-narrative.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/14/on-narrative.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-13T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-14T12:48:05-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2002, Henry Jenkins published the article &lt;em&gt;Game Design as Narrative Architecture&lt;/em&gt;. In it, he addresses many of my misgivings about the views Jesper Juul expresses in his &lt;em&gt;A Clash Between Games and Narrative&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Games Telling Stories?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following decade, we have witnessed the emergence of many innovative experiences that have advanced the state of the art in many of the categories Jenkins proposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="transmedia-storytelling"&gt;Transmedia Storytelling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experience franchises spreading to diverse media is nothing new. Look no further than the superhero characters from comics appearing in books, movies, television, web-series, and games. More interesting is the phenomenon of interactive experiences that transcend media boundaries. A recent example is Google's Ingress, a worldwide multiplayer alternate reality game that enables player participation through smartphone-world interaction, online code breaking, and storytelling/partaking through online videos and social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="spatial-narratives"&gt;Spatial Narratives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gone Home&lt;/em&gt; is a perfect example of what Jenkins calls a "Memory Palace," a place that players can explore at will, unravelling stories left in narrative fragments throughout a space. While &lt;em&gt;Gone Home&lt;/em&gt; communicates one primary narrative, that of the protagonist's sister, it also contains several tangentially-related story threads involving the other members of the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="micronarratives"&gt;Micronarratives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most modern games, particularly big budget titles, embed many "memorable moments" into their games. Some of these are developed to the extent that they are known as "side-quests," with mostly self-contained, sometimes optional narrative arcs that may enhance the primary storyline or serve as exercises in world-building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Punch Drunk's &lt;em&gt;Sleep No More&lt;/em&gt; is particularly notable in this category. It encourages audiences to explore a mass of related but distinct narrative threads at their own pace as they follow actors and explore a physical three story building with maze-like passages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="emergent-narratives"&gt;Emergent Narratives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unplanned narratives often emerge from games with large player-bases. The space game &lt;em&gt;Eve Online&lt;/em&gt; is a prime example; it provides a sandbox-like simulation environment with enough constraints that players self-organize to take on roles in many different stories involving themes such as faction conflict, diplomacy, corporate espionage, and piracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to me, however, that very few experiences explore smaller-scale emergent storytelling, especially in the category of single-player computer games with an emphasis on player choice. Some of the best games in this category (such as the fantastic &lt;em&gt;Spelunky&lt;/em&gt;) involve procedurally generated worlds and enemies and explore few emotions unrelated to conquest.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Beyond Definitions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/07/beyond-definitions.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/07/beyond-definitions.html</id>
    <published>2014-09-06T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-07T22:31:54-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What constitutes a &lt;em&gt;game&lt;/em&gt;? What constitutes &lt;em&gt;play&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophers, academics, and game creators have been debating the answers to questions of this ilk for a very long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Rules of Play&lt;/em&gt;, Katie Salen and Eric Zimmerman describe a game as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a system in which players engage in an artificial conflict,
defined by rules, that results in a quantifiable outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Definition of Play, The Classification of Games&lt;/em&gt;, Roger Caillois describes play via the properties &lt;em&gt;Free&lt;/em&gt; (voluntary), &lt;em&gt;Separate&lt;/em&gt; (with predefined limits of space and time), &lt;em&gt;Uncertain&lt;/em&gt; (the results are not guaranteed beforehand), &lt;em&gt;Unproductive&lt;/em&gt; (creating nothing of value during the course of the game and ending in a situation identical to that prior to the beginning of the game), &lt;em&gt;Governed by Rules&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Make-believe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesper Juul's definition of "game" (from &lt;em&gt;The Game, the Player, the World: Looking for a Heart of Gameness&lt;/em&gt;) is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a rule-based formal system with a variable and quantifiable outcome,
where different outcomes are assigned different values, the player
exerts effort in order to influence the outcome, the player feels
attached to the outcome, and the consequences of the activity are
optional and negotiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many conflicting definitions that Molleindustria created a &lt;a href="http://www.gamedefinitions.com"&gt;whole site&lt;/a&gt; devoted to game definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great variety suggests that it is futile to determine one true meaning for these terms; that they are simply ambiguous and context-dependent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, rather than ignoring them, I think that designers can think of them as artificial constraints to surmount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, does an experience really have to have a "variable and quantifiable outcome" to be considered a game? Why not try to create an emotionally moving interactive experience that involves an emotional journey but doesn't vary in its outcome?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does play truly have to be "unproductive"? What about games that involve creating lasting artifacts and social change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to envision experiences that challenge specific definitions seems like a fantastic way to develop games that have yet to be experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Set, System Analysis</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/01/set-analysis.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/09/01/set-analysis.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-31T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-01T22:29:17-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm studying how systems work at &lt;a href="http://interactive.usc.edu"&gt;USC's Interactive Media and Games Division&lt;/a&gt;, and I decided to explore how the design of Set cards is tied to the rules for the game. I initially wrote this with no resources other than a deck of Set cards and a Python interpreter, but I have since amended some of my initial impressions after reading &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Set_(game)"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can use playing cards in myriad ways, including building card castles, throwing cards at targets, using cards to propel projectiles, floating cards down streams ala &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poohsticks"&gt;Poohsticks&lt;/a&gt;, laying cards side-by side like dominos, and bending cards to create three dimensional shapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Set_(game)"&gt;Set&lt;/a&gt; is a simple card game with a deck of 81 standard-size playing cards that are uniquely suited for exactly one purpose that doesn't involve the destruction of the cards: for playing the game of Set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side of each Set card bears the logo of the game on a matte surface, while the other is devoted to one or more large symbols displayed on a glossy white canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symbols on any given card can differ in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quantity (each card has one, two, or three symbols)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Color (a given symbol can be green, red, or purple, and all symbols on a card share the same color)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shading (symbols can be solid-colored, striped in parallel with the longest side of the card, or consist of empty - outlines, and all symbols on a given card share the same shading)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shape (each symbol on a card is either tilde-shaped, diamond-shaped, or capsule-shaped, and each symbol on a given card has the same shape)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that each of these four properties has exactly three variants, which allows for the &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;code&gt;=81&lt;/code&gt; unique cards in the deck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, it would be impossible to play a standard match-2 game with a Set deck; by virtue of having three variants for each property, the game materials are optimized for 3-card combinations. The logo of the game reinforces this notion; it contains a visualization of stacks of three cards with different shading, calling to mind the card properties.
While there are &lt;code&gt;511920&lt;/code&gt; unique 3-card combinations possible in a deck of Set cards, not all of these combinations can be meaningful. If every 3-card combination with at least one shared property variant were considered a "match," then around &lt;code&gt;36%&lt;/code&gt; of the possible combinations would qualify, which would eliminate much of the depth present in the Set card game. Instead, a match, known as a "Set," occurs when each property varies either entirely or not at all. People playing the game compete to find and collect as many such Sets as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following three cards form a Set because they all have the same quantity variant but differ in every other property:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;3-Green-Empty-Tilde&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;3-Purple-Solid-Capsule&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;3-Red-Shaded-Diamond&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cards do not form a Set because two of the cards have the solid shading variant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;3-Green-Empty-Tilde&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;3-Purple-Solid-Capsule&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;3-Red-Solid-Diamond&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only around 1% of the possible 3-card combinations are Sets. However, the probability of discovering a 3-card Set in a collection of &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; cards increases quite quickly with &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the probabilities of a Set in a given collection of &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; cards drawn from the deck at random, at the start of the game (determined via numerical simulation in Python, using &lt;code&gt;100,000&lt;/code&gt; samples for each &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;-card collection):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Graph" src="/thoughts/images/2014-09-01-set-analysis/graph.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Card games typically involve cards held in the player's hands, but holding more than seven cards is ungainly, and there is only a 39% chance that seven random cards will contain a Set. Furthermore, the size and position of the symbols on the cards does not afford holding several of them in a hand; doing so obscures the property information which is integral to forming Sets. The cards are clearly designed to be placed face up on a level surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the diagram above, we can see that we get increasingly diminishing returns in the probability that an initial collection of n cards will contain a Set for &lt;code&gt;n&amp;gt;10&lt;/code&gt;. In fact, for &lt;code&gt;n=20&lt;/code&gt; and greater, the probability is &lt;code&gt;100%&lt;/code&gt;. When &lt;code&gt;n=12&lt;/code&gt;, the quantity used in the game of Set, the probability is initially &lt;code&gt;97%&lt;/code&gt; (although it quickly drops to about &lt;code&gt;93%&lt;/code&gt; as the game progresses and Sets are removed and replaced with new cards from the deck). Furthermore, the average amount of Sets present in a collection increases rapidly with &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;. For the sake of challenging players to find Sets, &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; should never be too high, so &lt;code&gt;n=12&lt;/code&gt; is a logical choice, although it does sometimes require the addition of new cards from the deck when no Sets are present (the rules to Set call for the addition of three new cards in this situation, which ensures that the amount of face-up cards on the table is always divisible by the amount of cards in a Set). Elegantly, &lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;4x3&lt;/code&gt;, the number of properties multiplied by the number of variants for each property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there are several &lt;a href="http://magliery.com/Set/SetVariants.html"&gt;Set variants&lt;/a&gt;, I would argue that the cards for Set are perfectly designed to match the primary game for which they were created, and that many of these alterations oppose the simplicity of the core game and/or the design of the cards. For example, the variants frequently call for holding some cards in one's hand, removing cards, or adding betting tokens. Nonetheless, I applaud the ingenuity of the player base.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Criticism</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/08/30/criticism.html"/>
    <id>http://jceipek.com/articles/2014/08/30/criticism.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-29T17:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2014-09-01T21:40:19-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julian Ceipek</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Design is all about constraints. Designers must be able to work within limitations, and the designs they create guide user interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've been thinking about how the constraints in some systems influence the way we engage with other systems. This idea is tied to the concept of consistency in interaction design. As Norman explains in &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Design-Everyday-Things-Donald-Norman/dp/0465067107"&gt;The Design of Everyday Things&lt;/a&gt;, the conceptual model for how we expect something to behave influences how we interact with it, and we take our knowledge of existing systems with us when we interact with others. Left-clicking in computer apps is a simple example: we expect to left-click to select virtual objects in drawing applications. When we encounter an application that breaks this convention, like &lt;a href="http://blender.org/"&gt;Blender&lt;/a&gt;, we experience what Cooper &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Inmates-Are-Running-Asylum/dp/0672326140"&gt;(The Inmates are Running the Asylum)&lt;/a&gt; calls cognitive friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After witnessing the &lt;a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/future-proof/2014/08/tropes-vs-anita-sarkeesian-passing-anti-feminist-nonsense-critique"&gt;deplorable&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.zenofdesign.com/our-growing-fuckwad-culture-problem/"&gt;behavior&lt;/a&gt; perpetuated by a subset of the people who identify themselves as "Gamers," I spent some time reflecting on the reasons behind their outrage at whom they bafflingly brand "Social Justice Warriors," as if that could possibly be a pejorative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm certain that part of the problem is simply that old standby, fear of change. However, I think it might also be affected by the the proliferation of binary experiences, both in games and across social media platforms. For many users, the core interaction with the latter is content consumption augmented with an expression of  "thumbs up" or "thumbs down." In many games, players take on the role of an unassailable hero or anti-hero character who is always justified in whatever he (because characters in games are rarely female) does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder if the constraints inherent in these experiences have trained people to to view the world in binary, to view criticism as condemnation rather than constructive critique.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
